{"tossups": [{"question": "1. Repeated attempts by members of this ethnicity to flee persecution helped necessitate the closure of the Torugart Pass. Nationalists of this ethnicity took advantage of a civil war to proclaim an autonomous government named for the mythic man Alash. They\u2019re not Ukrainians, but 1.3 million members of this ethnic group died in the so-called \u201cGoloschkein\u201d famine from 1932 to 1933. These people took to the streets in December 1986 after the sacking of a General Secretary of this ethnicity and his replacement with an ethnic (*) Russian; those riots were called Jeltoqsan. People of this ethnicity were the main victims of fallout from the Semipalatinsk test site. The Soviet Socialist Republic named for this ethnic group is where Trofim Lysenko enacted the Virgin Lands Campaign. Nursultan Nazarbayev belongs to, for 10 points, what ethnic group whose namesake republic once had its capital in Almaty?", "answer": "Kazakhs &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "2. One of these animals tries to bite the arm of an angel in his path as he \u201cgallops about doing good\u201d in a poem by Stevie Smith. Another poem claims these animals can \u201cspraggle upon waggle\u201d and ends \u201cFor he can swim for life.\u00a0For he can creep.\u201d That list-formatted poem by Christopher Smart is about Jeoffry. Another poem about one of these animals is set near a vase which \u201cChina\u2019s gayest art had dyed\u201d with \u201cazure flowers\u201d and laments \u201cNo dolphin came, no Nereid stirred\u201d to its aid. That poem originated the phrase \u201cNor all that (*) glisters, gold.\u201d Another series of poems about these animals claims that they must have \u201cthree different names\u201d and include the conjuring Mr. Mistoffelees and the criminal Macavity. Those poems are from T. S. Eliot\u2019s \u201cOld Possum\u2019s Book of\u201d these Practical\u201d animals. For 10 points, Thomas Gray wrote about the drowning of what pet Selima in a tub of goldfish?", "answer": "cat &lt;JC, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "3. This politician\u2019s actions on LGBT rights include signing an Insurance Equality Act guaranteeing coverage for same-sex partners and an expansion of the Unruh Rights Act, the latter on the same day as his veto of a same-sex marriage bill. Marsy\u2019s Law, enacted during this politician\u2019s tenure as governor, provided grounds for the family of Louis Santos to sue his administration after the sentence of Esteban Nu\u00f1ez was commuted. While campaigning, this man was criticized for meeting with Enron executives at the Peninsula Hotel after his predecessor suffered a massive drop in popularity due to (*) blackouts caused in part by Enron\u2019s fraud. This politician, who admitted to an affair with Mildred Patricia Baena, his housekeeper, was elected as governor in a recall election that ousted Gray Davis. For 10 points, name this Governor of California from 2003 to 2011 and star of the Terminator series.", "answer": "Arnold Schwarzenegger [accept either underlined portion; accept Ahnuld] &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "4. Carl Ernst posited that this text uses a form of symmetrical arrangement between the beginning and end called \u201cring composition.\u201d The density of literary devices in this text is often used as an argument for its literary inimitability, which is commonly stated as a challenge to produce a \u201cchapter like it.\u201d In a book titled this work \u201cin context,\u201d Angelika Neuwirth suggests that it be considered as a product of Late Antiquity. A commentary titled for being \u201cIn the Shade of\u201d this other text was written while the author was (*) imprisoned for an assassination attempt; that commentary, along with the book Milestones, serves as a manifesto for Qutbism. A section of this text talking about three daughters of God was later edited out and formed the basis of a Salman Rushdie novel. For 10 points, name this book that once contained the \u201cSatanic Verses\u201d and is divided into 114 chapters called surahs.", "answer": "al-Qur\u2019an [or Koran] &lt;EM, Literary Legacy&gt;", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion"}, {"question": "5. Re-interpretation of texts written under this empire\u2019s rule was the primary goal of Matthew Restall and James Lockhart, members of the New Philology movement. Alexander Hill Everett used his diplomatic post to send documents about this empire\u2019s history to his friend William Scott Prescott for use in his three books on it. The term for a process begun by this empire\u2019s foreign forays was coined by the title of a 1972 book by Alfred Crosby, the author of Ecological Imperialism. A \u201cpolitical essay\u201d on this empire\u2019s holdings was written by (*) Alexander von Humboldt. Within this empire\u2019s caste system, \u201cpeninsular\u201d people were given the most privileges. Supposedly unrivaled cruelty by this empire was the subject of the \u201cBlack Legend,\u201d furthered by sympathetic priests who translated native documents like the Florentine Codex. For 10 points, name this empire which conquered the Aztecs.", "answer": "Spanish empire [or Spain or Spanish Bourbon empire or Hapsburg empire; prompt on Holy Roman Empire; prompt on Bourbon empire; do not accept or prompt on \u201cAustrian empire\u201d or \u201cAustria\u201d] &lt;WA, Historiography&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "6. In the 77th year of this century, the Great Council of Ragusa determined European quarantining to be a period of thirty days. Sir Michael Postan\u2019s thesis argues that demographic trends in the century before this one contributed to this century\u2019s \u201cMalthusian crisis.\u201d The Sack of Limoges and the First Castilian Civil War are described in a primary source recounting this century. This century is labeled \u201ccalamitous\u201d in the subtitle of (*) Barbara Tuchman\u2019s A Distant Mirror. The fifteenth through seventeenth years of this century witnessed a general population collapse throughout Europe due to a Great Famine chronicled by Jean Froissart, in contrast to the extensive population growth of the prior centuries. In this century, increasing tax burdens and passage of acts like the Statute of Laborers led to uprisings like France\u2019s Jacquerie and England\u2019s Peasants\u2019 Revolt. For 10 points, identify this century in which the Black Death wiped out a third of Europe\u2019s population.", "answer": "14th century CE [or 14th century AD; or 1300s CE; or 1300s AD] &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "7. The voice of one of these objects is possessed by a \u201chalf-bodied baby\u201d that rises from ashes after it is killed by Tutuola\u2019s palm-wine drinkard and his wife. In a novel named for one of these physical objects, the protagonist is told that Gone with the Wind is a documentary, and her mother slips messages like \u201cAmerica is cruel.\u00a0Consider kindness\u201d into the linens she delivers. In that work, \u201cthe Watchman\u201d yells prophecies during a fire after killing his employers and Paul H. with a machete. Jim and Abby rather notably use one of these devices in (*) Nicholson Baker\u2019s Vox. Clare Savage is killed in a guerilla resistance in Michelle Cliff\u2019s sequel to Abeng named for \u201cNo\u201d [one of these objects] \u201cTo Heaven.\u201d For 10 points, John O\u2019Hara\u2019s BUtterfield 8 is named after a code used for what devices, which are referenced in the title of Dial M for Murder?", "answer": "telephones &lt;JC, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "8. In a story by this author, a disoriented new immigrant from Bombay moves to D.C. and finds himself annoyed by the \u201cbad sanskrit\u201d of the white Hare Krishnas in his neighborhood. That character, Santosh, later marries the \u201chubshi\u201d woman who takes care of his apartment. Dayo is driven out of operating his roti-shop after moving to England in another of this author\u2019s stories. This author of \u201cOne Out of Many\u201d and \u201cTell Me Who To Kill\u201d wrote a story in which a (*) Zulu man spits on Linda\u2019s husband, Bobby, after he flirts with him while traveling through a fictional African country. Man Man and Bogart are two characters who frequently appear in a collection by this author titled for a neighborhood in Port of Spain, where he also set a novel about a man who desires to please his Tulsi in-laws with the title structure. For 10 points name this author of \u201cIn a Free State,\u201d Miguel Street, and A House for Mr. Biswas.", "answer": "V.\u00a0S. Naipaul &lt;SB, Short Fiction&gt;", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "9. Note to players: Type of work and author required. One of these works complains about \u201cthat second-hand school of poetry\u201d in the context of discussing reviews by Blackwood\u2019s Edinburgh Magazine. Some of these works boast of \u201chundreds\u201d of \u201cpl &amp; opt Cs,\u201d a shorthand the author borrowed from the Satyricon to refer to sex, such as in the context of Nicolo Giraud. Another of these works lambasts \u201cTurdsworth,\u201d echoing a criticism that their author made of Wordsworth and Robert Southey in Canto I of a poem. One of these works is burned in front of Lady Croom by (*) Septimus Hodge in Tom Stoppard\u2019s Arcadia. Many of these works are addressed to Teresa, Contessa Guiccioli [ghee-CHOH-lee], the author\u2019s lover in Ravenna, and many others are to Percy Shelley. One of them says \u201cIf I am a poet\u2026 the air of Greece has made me one.\u201d For 10 points, identify these epistles by the author of \u201cManfred\u201d and \u201cDon Juan.\u201d", "answer": "letters by Lord Byron &lt;WA, Authors/Bios&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "10. At the end of this play\u2019s second act, a character vows to prove to his wife \u201chow far [he is] from jealousy or fear.\u201d Two characters in this play discuss the legend of a townsman named Mass Stone, who supposedly worked as a spy and smuggled secrets written on cabbages out of the Netherlands. A servant in this play explains that he abandoned his vow of silence because the spirit of a lawyer had possessed him. An acrostic poem that spells out the name of the title character appears in this play\u2019s (*) \u201cArgument,\u201d which comes before its prologue. The title character of this play disguises himself as the Scoto Mantua and sings a song praising his fake potion in front of Sir Politic Would Be. Nano and Castrone are two servants of this play's title character, who listens to Mosca and spurns prostitutes to pursue the beautiful Celia. For 10 points, name this play about a rich fox-like Venetian by Ben Jonson.", "answer": "Volpone &lt;SB, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "11. Hellenistic Greeks created varieties of these objects called thureoi that copied Celtic designs. After the Battle of Gabiene, an elite group named for examples of these objects handed over their commander Eumenes to Antigonus the One-Eyed in exchange for their baggage train. Plutarch records that the phrase \u201c\u0112 t\u0101n \u0113 epi tas,\u201d which refers to these items, was spoken to departing men in (*) Sparta by their wives. An iconic example of these items from Classical Greece was called the aspis, with a specific variety being called a hoplon. An example of this item called a scutum was carried by Roman legionaries, who would use it to form a testudo or \u201ctortoise\u201d formation. For 10 points, name these typically wooden objects used by soldiers to protect themselves in battle.", "answer": "shields [accept Silver Shields; accept aspis or hoplon before they are read; accept \u201cwith this shield or on it] &lt;WA, Ancient History&gt; Note to moderator: Read the answerline carefully before starting.", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "12. One of these institutions dealt with the issue of \u201cseparating hard and white.\u201d These institutions refined the original methods of \u201ccorrelative thinking.\u201d Lewis Maverick wrote that the Physiocrats modeled themselves on one of these institutions, which contended that the man who introduced \u201cfive cereals\u201d for cultivation was the ideal king. In a story from one of these institutions, kings needing to sate people\u2019s conflicting desires is the origin of rituals. One of these institutions that promulgated such ideas as \u201ca white horse is not a horse\u201d was named after (*) \u201cnames.\u201d The so-called \u201cGolden Age of Chinese Philosophy\u201d is known as the \u201ccontention\u201d of one hundred of these institutions. For 10 points, name these institutions, of which only a few outside of Legalism survived when Qin Shi Huangdi initiated the \u201cburning of books and killing of scholars.\u201d", "answer": "The Hundred Schools of Thought from the Zhou Dynasty/Warring States Period [or zh\u016bz\u01d0 b\u01ceiji\u0101; accept nine schools of thought; accept schools (of thought) in ancient China; accept schools during the Han Dynasty; accept schools during the Qin Dynasty; accept schools during the Warring States Period; accept schools during the Zhou Dynasty; prompt on schools by asking \u201cduring what era?\u201d and expect one of the aforementioned answers; prompt on Chinese philosophies or similar such answers before mention of \u201cChinese Philosophy\u201d; prompt on any answer suggesting a philosophical movement] &lt;AA, Phil/SS&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "13. A leader of this country wrote a violently racist essay in which he denounced Chinese as the \u201cJews of the East.\u201d Cultivation of cane sugar and rubber were both introduced to this country in the early 19th century by Chinese immigrants, especially Teochews, who were said to rise from \u201cmat to riches.\u201d Chinese people in this country created the markets of Sampheng and invented the drink that became Red Bull. The lands of this modern-day country were unified by a (*) general of Chinese birth named Taksin. Thanks to extensive immigration and assimilation, this non-U.S. country has the largest Overseas Chinese population in the world, and Chinese are estimated to control 90 percent of its corporations. For 10 points, name this country whose leaders of Chinese ancestry have included the Shinawatras, who were overthrown in coups in Bangkok.", "answer": "Kingdom of Thailand [or Kingdom of Siam; accept any answer referring to the Thai people or Thai kingdom] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "14. A female author from this country broke taboos by openly depicting female desire in her novel Love in Excess. The play Almyna exemplifies dramatic forms of a genre pioneered by female authors in this country called \u201camatory fiction.\u201d Seventy-two years of diaries, the first of which is addressed to \u201cNobody,\u201d were kept by a female author from this country. A female author from here created a heroine who discovers a human figure made of wax behind a black veil and is helped by the servant (*) Ludovico, who works for a bandit nobleman. An author from this country created such villains as Schedoni [skeh-DOH-nee] and Montoni, the latter of whom owns the title castle investigated by Emily St.\u00a0Aubert. For 10 points, name this home country of Eliza Haywood, Frances Burney, and Mysteries of Udolpho author Ann Radcliffe.", "answer": "England [or Great Britain or the United Kingdom or UK] &lt;WA, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "15. In one work named after this figure, Marcellus attempts to stab this man in the back but is suddenly unable to, and kills himself in remorse. In that play, this man watches as his wife is poisoned with a peach, and he accumulates followers who chant \u201cDeath is dead!\u201d and continually perform the title action. A poem named after this figure lists \u201cA cake of soap / A wedding ring / A gold filling\u201d and asks \u201cPeel off the napkin\u2026 Do I terrify?\u201d (*) Sonya reads a passage about this man to Raskolnikov in Crime and Punishment. This figure, who \u201cLaughed\u201d in a Eugene O\u2019Neill drama, titles a poem that states \u201cDying / is an art, like everything else\u201d and concludes \u201cBeware.\u00a0/ Out of the ash / I rise with my red hair / and I eat men like air.\u201d That poem by Sylvia Plath is named after \u201cLady\u201d [this character]. For 10 points, name this Biblical figure from Bethany whom Jesus resurrects.", "answer": "Lazarus &lt;JC, Miscellaneous Lit&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "16. In an essay, this author divided novelists into two \u201ccamps,\u201d the preachers and teachers, headed by Tolstoy and Dickens, and the pure artists, headed by Austen and Turgenev, and described how E. M. Forster attempted to straddle both camps. In another essay, this author wrote about the death of a creature that looked as \u201cif someone had taken a tiny bead of pure life\u201d and \u201chad set it dancing and zig zagging to show us the true nature of life.\u201d This author compiled three essays about Henry (*) James into one collection, whose title essay is about an insect that admits \u201cdeath is stronger than I am.\u201d An essay by this author of \u201cDeath of the Moth\u201d was written for her \u201cWomen and Fiction\u201d lectures and includes a section on Judith Shakespeare. For 10 points name this author of \"A Room of One's Own.\"", "answer": "Virginia Woolf &lt;SB, Essays/Crit&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "17. This organization\u2019s adoption of violent guerrilla tactics caused a split with other organizations in the Autonomist movement, which the government still targeted for arrest. People accused of supporting this organization who fled to France were protected from extradition under the \u201cMitterrand doctrine,\u201d such as an intellectual who later published the books Commonwealth and Multitude. It\u2019s not a political party, but a \u201cFront of Firmness\u201d opposing this group was maintained by ideological allies of it who had accepted the Historic Compromise, such as (*) Enrico Berlinguer. This was the main left-wing group behind violent acts that exemplified the \u201cstrategy of tension\u201d during the 1970s and 1980s, such as when it killed the leader of the Christian Democrat party at the height of the Years of Lead. For 10 points, name this terrorist group that kidnapped Aldo Moro, the Prime Minister of Italy.", "answer": "Red Brigades [or Brigate Rossi] &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "18. During an incident on this island, wounded soldiers ate lettuce while whispering \u201crun, rabbit, run\u201d as a form of dissent. Ken G.\u00a0Hall won an Academy Award for his film about military action on this island, which he sourced from newsreels taken by Damien Parer. Sydney Rowell and Arthur Allen were dismissed during a campaign on this island conducted by the Maroubra Force. The Dobodura base on this island was used to scramble planes to defend from aerial assaults in Operation I-Go. Soldiers on one side of a campaign on this island were assisted by natives called the (*) \u201cFuzzy-Wuzzy Angels.\u201d Control of this island\u2019s Owen Stanley Range was contested during the Kokoda Track Campaign, which, like the Battle of the Coral Sea, sought to prevent Japanese control of Port Moresby. For 10 points, name this island also known as Papua.", "answer": "New Guinea [or Niugini or Irian Jaya; accept Papua until \u201cPapua\u201d is read] &lt;EM, British/Other History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "19. In one work, a story is told about a character who spared this man\u2019s life when he fainted, only for this man to fail to spare him in return; that work describes this man sitting on a log ordering men to cross a river and not watching as they drown. An author who poked fun at \u201cThe Second Funeral\u201d of this man also created a woman who profits from selling her horse at inflated prices to Joseph Sedley during a panic caused by his actions. A would-be Freemason symbolically proves this man is the (*) Antichrist and tries to assassinate him in a novel that uses him as an instance of a historical \u201cgreat man.\u201d Dostoevsky\u2019s Raskolnikov claims that he wants to become like this man, whom Pierre Bezukhov seeks to kill. For 10 points, name this Frenchman who is fought at Borodino in the novel War and Peace.", "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte [accept either name; or Napoleon I; or Napoleone di Buonaparte] &lt;JC, HistInLit&gt;", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "20. A work made of this material containing several \u201cadmonitions\u201d addressed to the Lord of All is of interest to Biblical scholars for noting that a river is made of blood. Karl Lepsius probably illegally acquired an object made of this material that depicts five stories of priests and magicians. A fragmented object made of this material drew controversy in 2012 for claiming to depict Jesus\u2019 wife, but is likely a forgery. Examples of this material used to record medical practices were collected by (*) George Ebers and Edwin Smith. A work made of this material called \u201cWestcar\u201d covers the reigns of Sneferu and Khufu. This material was made of strips of Cyperus that may have been glued together, and generally preserved well in dry climes like Egypt. For 10 points, name this ancient writing material, the name of which gives English its word \u201cpaper.\u201d", "answer": "papyrus [or papyri; do not accept or prompt on \u201cpaper\u201d] &lt;WA, Historical Sources&gt;", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion"}, {"question": "21. In August 2017, more than 50 acres of Roman ruins were found off the coast of this country near the town of Nabeul. A mosaic found in this non-China country from the 4th century AD depicting Dominus Julius and his estate is in its Bardo Museum. A huge amphitheater that could hold 35,000 people can be seen in the ruins of Thysdrus in this country. The presidential palace of this country is found near the Baths of Antoninus Pius. A 2013 paper by Paolo Xella et al.\u00a0argued that (*) child cemeteries found in this country contained the victims of sacrifices at tophets. Stones taken from ruins in this country were used to build additions to the Great Mosque of Kairouan. This country contains the ruins of Utica, which served as the capital of the Roman province of Africa. For 10 points, name this North African country which contains the ruins of Carthage.", "answer": "(Republic of) Tunisia &lt;WA, Archaeology&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "22. This poem\u2019s speaker cannot remember if he made plans with Phyllis \u201cwho had two dimples in her cheeks,\u201d on Christopher Street ten years ago. The speaker of this poem tells its addressee that he has forgotten her name and goes on to list possible names, including \u201cMelusina, Laura, Isabel, Persephone,\u201d and \u201cMary.\u201d The epigraph to this poem quotes the opening lines of Gerard de Nerval\u2019s poem \u201cArtemis.\u201d An abruptly short line in this poem consists only of the words \u201cMadrid, (*) 1937.\u201d This poem frequently repeats variations of the line \u201cI go amongst your body as among the world\u201d and it begins and ends with the same six lines, which reference a river that \u201cdoubles back, and comes full circle.\u201d Its 584 lines are meant to mirror the number of days in Venus\u2019s synodic orbit. For 10 points, name this poem which begins describing a \u201cwillow of crystal, a poplar of water,\u201d written by Octavio Paz.", "answer": "\u201cSunstone\u201d [or \u201cPiedra del sol\u201d] &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "23. A man with this surname suggests that a bank\u2019s investigating committee moved several photographs when he is accused by a woman of doing so, after which he begins crying out his own name. That character with this surname discusses \u201cthe lie made into the rule of the world\u201d after a priest convinces him that a \u201ccheating\u201d character in a story was himself deceived. Another character with this last name survives by lowering a teaspoon down a well for water and is detained in a prison camp as a (*) \u201cCM.\u201d That character with this last name carries his mother\u2019s ashes in a wheelbarrow to Prince Albert. A character with this surname hears the parable \u201cBefore the Law\u201d and dies \u201clike a dog\u201d after being accused of an unknown crime. For 10 points, name this last initial of the harelipped gardener Michael created by J. M. Coetzee, as well as Josef, the protagonist of The Trial.", "answer": "K. [accept Michael K. or Josef K.] &lt;JC, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "24. This city is home to the oldest prison in the U.S., the notorious Ash Street Jail. A major 1958 volcanic eruption in the Azores triggered the second wave of mass Portuguese migration to this city, helping cement it as the \u201cPortuguese capital of America.\u201d Wamsutta Mills was a major center of this city\u2019s textile industry, which was affected by a 1928 strike organized by the Communist Party. It was called the \u201cfugitive\u2019s Gibraltar\u201d for hosting many escaped slaves, including Box Brown and Frederick Douglass. This city became known as (*) \u201cThe City that Lit the World\u201d in the mid-19th century because, thanks to its deeper natural harbor, it supplanted Nantucket as the hub of the industry that supplied most of America\u2019s heating oil, as well as spermaceti and other products. For 10 points, name this city in southern Massachusetts that was historically the most important whaling port in the U.S.", "answer": "New Bedford &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}